Chapter 22.
A warm wind.
[Music]
And so Wilbur came home to his beloved manure pile in the barn cellar. His was
a strange homecoming. Around his neck, he wore a medal of honor. In his mouth,
he held a sack of spider's eggs. "There is no place like home," Wilbur thought
as he placed Charlotte's 514 unborn children carefully in a safe corner.
"The barn smelled good. His friends, the sheep, and the geese, were glad to see
him back. The geese gave him a noisy welcome. "Congratulations,"
they cried. "Nice work!" Mr. Zuckerman took the metal from Wilbur's neck and
hung it on a nail over the pig pin where visitors could examine it. Wilbur
himself could look at it whenever he wanted to.
In the days that followed, he was very happy. He grew to a great size. He no
longer worried about being killed, for he knew that Mr. Zuckerman would keep
him as long as he lived. Wilbur often thought of Charlotte. A few strands of
her old web still hung in the doorway.
Every day Wilbur would stand and look at the torn, empty web, and a lump would
come to his throat. No one had ever had such a friend so affectionate, so loyal,
and so skillful.
The autumn days grew shorter. Lurvy brought the squashes and the pumpkins in
from the garden and piled them on the barn floor where they wouldn't get
nipped on frosty nights. The maples and birches turned bright colors, and the
wind shook them, and they dropped their leaves one by one to the ground.
Under the wild apple trees in the pasture, the red little apples lay thick
on the ground, and the sheep gnawed them, and the geese noded them, and
foxes came in the night and sniffed them. One evening, just before
Christmas, snow began falling. It covered house and barn and fields and
woods. Wilbur had never seen snow before.
When morning came, he went out and plowed the drifts in his yard for the
fun of it. Fern and Avery arrived, dragging a sled. They coasted down the
lane and out onto the frozen pond in the pasture. "Costing is the most fun there
is," said Avery. "The most fun there is," retorted Fern. is when the ferris
wheel stops and Henry and I are in the top car and Henry makes the car swing
and we can see everything for miles and miles and miles.
Goodness, are you still thinking about that old ferris wheel? said Avery in
disgust. The fair was weeks and weeks ago. I think about it all the time, said
Fern, picking snow from her ear.
After Christmas, the thermometer dropped to 10 below zero. Cold settled on the
world. The pasture was bleak and frozen.
The cows stayed in the barn all the time now, except on sunny mornings when they
went out and stood in the barnyard in the lee of the straw pile. The sheep
stayed near the barn, too, for protection. When they were thirsty, they
ate snow. The geese hung around the barnyard the way boys hang around a
drugstore, and Mr. Zuckerman fed them corn and turnipss to keep them cheerful.
"Many, many, many, many things," they always said when they saw the food coming.
Templeton moved indoors when winter came. His ratty home under the pig
trough was too chilly, so he fixed himself a cozy nest in the barn behind
the grain bins. He lined it with bits of dirty newspapers and rags, and whenever
he found a trinket or a keepsake, he carried it home and stored it there.
He continued to visit Wilbur three times a day, exactly at meal time, and Wilbur
kept the promise he had made. Wilbur let the rat eat first. Then, when Templeton
couldn't hold another mouthful, Wilbur would eat. As a result of overeating,
Templeton grew bigger and fatter than any rat you ever saw. He was gigantic.
He was as big as a young woodchuck.
The old sheep spoke to him about his size one day. "You would live longer,"
said the old sheep. "If you wait less."
"Who wants to live forever?" sneered the rat.
I am naturally a heavy eater, and I get untold satisfaction from the pleasures
of the feast. He patted his stomach, grinned at the sheep, and crept upstairs to lie down.
All winter, Wilbur watched over Charlotte's egg sack as though he were
guarding his own children. He had scooped out a special place in the
manure for the sack next to the board fence. On very cold nights he lay so
that his breath would warm it. For Wilbur nothing in life was so important
as this small round object. Nothing else mattered.
Patiently he awaited the end of winter and the coming of the little spiders.
Life is always a rich and steady time when you are waiting for something to
happen or to hatch. The winter ended at last.
I heard the frogs today, said the old sheep one evening. Listen, you can hear them now.
Wilbur stood still and cocked his ears.
From the pond, in shrill chorus, came the voices of hundreds of little frogs.
"Spring time," said the old sheep thoughtfully. "Another spring!"
As she walked away, Wilbur saw a new lamb following her. It was only a few
hours old. The snows melted and ran away. The streams and ditches bubbled
and chattered with rushing water.
A sparrow with a streaky breast arrived and sang. The light strengthened. The
mornings came sooner. Almost every morning there was another new lamb in
the sheepfold. The goose was sitting on nine eggs. The sky seemed wider and a
warm wind blew. The last remaining strands of Charlotte's old web floated away and vanished.
One fine sunny morning after breakfast, Wilbur stood watching his precious sack.
He wasn't thinking of anything much. As he stood there, he noticed something
move. He stepped closer and stared. A tiny spider crawled from the sack. It
was no bigger than a grain of sand, no bigger than the head of a pin. Its body
was gray with a black stripe underneath.
Its legs were gray and tan. It looked just like Charlotte.
Wilbur trembled all over when he saw it.
The little spider waved at him. Then Wilbur looked more closely. Two more
little spiders crawled out and waved.
They climbed round and round on the sack, exploring their new world. Then
three more little spiders. Then eight.
Then 10. Charlotte's children were here at last.
Wilbur's heart pounded. He began to squeal.
Then he raced in circles, kicking manure into the air. Then he turned a backflip.
Then he planted his front feet and came to a stop in front of Charlotte's
children. "Hello there," he said. The first spider said hello. But its voice
was so small, Wilbur couldn't hear it.
"I am an old friend of your mothers," said Wilbur. "I'm glad to see you. Are
you all right? Is everything all right?
The little spiders waved their four legs at him. Wilbur could see by the way they
acted that they were glad to see him. Is there anything I can get you? Is there
anything you need? The young spiders just waved.
For several days and several nights, they crawled here and there, up and
down, around and about, waving at Wilbur, trailing tiny drag lines behind
them and exploring their home. There were dozens and dozens of them. Wilbur
couldn't count them, but he knew that he had a great many new friends. They grew
quite rapidly. Soon, each was as big as a BB shot. They made tiny webs near the sack.
Then came a quiet morning when Mr.
Zuckerman opened a door on the north side. A warm draft of rising air blew
softly through the barn cellar. The air smelled of the damp earth, of the spruce
woods, of the sweet springtime.
The baby spiders felt the warm updraft.
One spider climbed to the top of the fence.
Then it did something that came as a great surprise to Wilbur. The spider
stood on its head, pointed its spinetses in the air, and let loose a cloud of
fine silk. The silk formed a balloon. As Wilbur watched, the spider let go of the
fence and rose into the air. "Goodbye," it said as it sailed through the
doorway. "Wait a minute," screamed Wilbur. Where do you think you're going?
But the spider was already out of sight.
Then another baby spider crawled to the top of the fence, stood on its head,
made a balloon, and sailed away. Then another spider. Then another. The air
was soon filled with tiny balloons. Each balloon carrying a spider.
Wilbur was frantic. Charlotte's babies were disappearing at a great rate. "Come
back, children," he cried. "Goodbye," they called. "Goodbye. Goodbye." At
last, one little spider took time enough to stop and talk to Wilbur before making
its balloon. "We are leaving here on the warm updraft.
This is our moment for setting forth. We are aeronauts, and we are going out into
the world to make webs for ourselves.
But where? asked Wilbur. Wherever the wind takes us, high, low, near, far,
east, west, north, south, we take to the breeze. We go as we please.
Are all of you going? asked Wilbur. You can't all go. I would be left alone with
no friends.
Your mother wouldn't want that to happen, I'm sure.
The air was now so full of balloonists that the barn cellar looked almost as
though a mist had gathered. Balloons by the dozens were rising, circling and
drifting away through the door, sailing off on the gentle wind. Cries of
goodbye, goodbye, came weakly to Wilbur's ears.
He couldn't bear to watch anymore. In sorrow, he sank to the ground and closed
his eyes. This seemed like the end of the world, to be deserted by Charlotte's
children. Wilbur cried himself to sleep.
When he woke, it was late afternoon. He looked at the egg sack. It was empty.
He looked into the air. The balloonists were gone. Then he walked dreily to the
doorway where Charlotte's Web used to be. He was standing there thinking of
her when he heard a small voice.
Salutations, it said. I'm up here. So am I, said another tiny voice. So am I,
said a third voice. Three of us are staying. We like this place, and we like you.
Wilbur looked up. At the top of the doorway, three small webs were being constructed.
On each web, working busily, was one of Charlotte's daughters.
Can I take this to mean, asked Wilbur, that you have definitely decided to live
here in the barn cellar and that I am going to have three friends?
You can indeed, said the spiders.
What are your names, please? asked Wilbur, trembling with joy. I'll tell
you my name, replied the first little spider. If you'll tell me why you are trembling.
I'm trembling with joy, said Wilbur.
Then my name is Joy, said the first spider. What was my mother's middle
initial? asked the second spider.
Hey, said Wilbur. Then my name is Aranea, said the spider. How about me?
asked the third spider. Will you just pick out a nice, sensible name for me?
Something not too long, not too fancy, and not too dumb.
Wilbur thought hard. Nelly, he suggested. Fine, I'd like that very
much, said the third spider. You may call me Nelly. She daintily fastened her
or blind to the next spoke of the web.
Wilbur's heart brimmed with happiness.
He felt that he should make a short speech on this very important occasion.
Joy, Arina, Nelly, he began. Welcome to the barn cellar.
You have chosen a hallowed doorway from which to string your webs. I think it is
only fair to tell you that I was devoted to your mother. I owe my very life to
her. She was brilliant, beautiful, and loyal to the end. I shall always
treasure her memory. To you, her daughters, I pledge my friendship forever and ever.
I pledge mine, said Joy. I do too, said Arana. And so do I, said Nelly, who had
just managed to catch a small gnat.
It was a happy day for Wilbur, and many more happy, tranquil days followed. As
time went on, and the months and years came and went, he was never without friends.
Fern did not come regularly to the barn anymore. She was growing up and was
careful to avoid childish things like sitting on a milk stool near a pig pin.
But Charlotte's children and grandchildren and greatgrandchildren
year after year lived in the doorway.
Each spring there were new little spiders hatching out to take the place
of the old. Most of them sailed away on their balloons, but always two or three
stayed and set up housekeeping in the doorway. Mr. Zuckerman took fine care of
Wilbur all the rest of his days, and the pig was often visited by friends and
admirers, for nobody ever forgot the year of his triumph and the miracle of the web.
Life in the barn was very good. Night and day, winter and summer, spring and
fall, dull days and bright days. It was the best place to be, thought Wilbur.
This warm delicious cellar with the geralous geese, the changing seasons,
the heat of the sun, the passage of swallows, the nearness of rats, the
sameness of sheep, the love of spiders, the smell of manure, and the glory of everything.
Wilbur never forgot Charlotte. Although he loved her children and grandchildren
dearly, none of the new spiders ever quite took her place in his heart. She
was in a class by herself.
It is not often that someone comes along who is a true friend and a good writer.
Charlotte was both.
at the end.
[Music]